Guide to the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral histories 2008.030
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Dabu, Joel, 2008 April 11; 2008.030.10
  In this interview, Joel Dabu discusses his work in community revitalization with Restoration and its emphasis on commercial rehabilitation and the Bedford-Stuyvesant Gateway Business Improvement District. He shares his views on redlining, segregation, and the construction and availability of affordable housing -- as well as possible negative effects such as gentrification and displacement. Dabu discusses the role local government can play in supporting community entrepreneurship and the possible effects of the 2008 economic recession. Interview conducted by Bahati Williams.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Discrimination in mortgage loans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Segregation |z United States; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Dabu, Joel; Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association
- Danois, David, 2008 May 5; 2008.030.11
  Born in a Jewish hospital in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1945, David Danois' early life was spent in Bedford-Stuyvesant and Queens. He returned permanently to Brooklyn to attend Pratt Institute's Martin Luther King Fellowship Program. Hired by Restoration while still attending Pratt, Danois worked as the staff architect and later became the vice president of Restoration's large housing rehabilitation program. At the time of the 2008 interview, Danois owned his own architecture firm, Danois Architects, which specialized in design for affordable housing.
  In this interview, David Danois describes his early involvement with Restoration as a staff architect. Danois discusses the workaday life at Restoration, challenges to affordable housing in Bedford-Stuyvesant and greater Brooklyn, and recent rapid increases in property values. He expresses his respect for the neighborhood's vibrancy and expresses optimism for its future. At the interview's end, Danois describes his current occupation as the owner of a small architecture firm which specializes in the development of affordable housing and condominiums in Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Danois, David; Patterson, George; Pratt Institute; Thomas, Franklin A.
- Edwards, Seth, 2008 April 29; 2008.030.12
  Seth Edwards was born in 1946 in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, the son of an Episcopalian missionary. Around age two, Edwards moved with his family to Liberia, where his father served as a medical missionary. During their time in Liberia, Edwards and his family would occasionally vacation with his grandparents in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. Edwards stayed in Liberia with his family until middle school, when he enrolled at a boarding school in Garden City, Long Island. Edwards graduated from Cornell University via a university in Liberia, which he attended on a Cornell exchange program. Soon after, Edwards was drafted into the United States Army and served in the Vietnam War from 1968 to 1969. Upon returning to America, Edwards joined JP Morgan Chase Bank. At the time of the 2008 interview, Edwards was a vice president within the bank's Global Philanthropy, Community Relations division.
  In this interview, Seth Edwards discusses his own life story, and his family's history and genealogy. He provides impressions of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn of his youth. Edwards recounts Bedford-Stuyvesant's economic and cultural renaissance, and describes the essential role played by Restoration in the community's evolution, sharing his thoughts on the tension between economic development and gentrification. At the interview's end, Edwards describes JP Morgan Chase Bank's philanthropic strategy. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Paris (France); Philanthropists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Edwards, Seth; Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History; United States. Army
- English, Josephine, 2008 April 29; 2008.030.13
  Dr. Josephine English was born in 1920 in Ontario, Virginia. After her mother's early death, English and her siblings were raised by her single father in Englewood, New Jersey. She attended Hunter College as an undergraduate, attained a master's degree in psychology from New York University; and went to medical school at the historically African American Meharry Medical School in Nashville, Tennessee. Upon graduation in 1949, Dr. English worked as one of New York's first African American female doctors at Harlem Hospital. After relocating to Brooklyn to work and live, Dr. English founded the Women's Health Center, Adelphi Medical Center, and the Paul Robeson Theater in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn. Dr. English died in 2011 at the age of ninety-one.
  In this interview, Dr. Josephine English relates stories from her life's history, including tales from her childhood and her career as a doctor. She details her experiences with sexism and racism, encountered during medical school and later, as a practicing obstetrician and gynecologist. She describes her achievements as an OB-GYN: Having delivered thousands of babies (including the six children of Malcom X and Betty Shabazz), and founding the Women's Health Center. Dr. English reflects on her community activism, including founding the Paul Robeson Theater, and the Adelphi Medical Center. She openly shares her personal opinions on the practice of medicine today as it relates to women and the indigent; her thoughts on modern social ills such as HIV, gentrification, and displacement; and her views on politics and religion. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Medicine |x Practice |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Racism; Theater |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Societies, etc.; Women |z United States |x Social conditions; Women's health services |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; English, Josephine, Dr.; Obama, Barack
- Fishman, Alan, 2008 May 14; 2008.030.14
  Alan Fishman grew up in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, where he played competitive basketball throughout the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn and attended Erasmus Hall High School. He attended Brown University as an undergraduate and holds a master's degree in economics from Columbia University. A commercial banker, Fishman's involvement with Restoration began in 1969. At the time of the 2008 interview, Fishman was a former president of Independence Community Bank, the current chairman of the Independence Community Foundation, the current chairman of the Brooklyn Academy of Music, and a significant supporter of Restoration.
  In this interview, Alan Fishman remembers growing up on the basketball courts of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, a period he recalls as important in his development. Fishman recounts Restoration's emergence from a time of financial challenges and discontinuity of leadership. He describes a collaboration between the Brooklyn Academy of Music and Restoration in the Dance Africa program, noting the rarity of such successful ventures. Fishman discusses the evolution of Bedford-Stuyvesant and the essential role played by cultural and leadership centers in the maintenance of a vibrant community. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.); Philanthropists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Brooklyn Academy of Music; Fishman, Alan; Grannum, Colvin W.; Thomas, Franklin A.; Youth Arts Academy
- Glascoe, Benjamin, 2007 August 31; 2008.030.15
  Benjamin A. Glascoe (1937- ) was born at St. Mary's Hospital and was raised in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. He played collegiate baseball and football for Shaw University, where he graduated in 1961. Glascoe's professional career began with the New York City Social Services Division, where he served as a case worker. From there, he was hired by Restoration in 1968, just months after its founding; his first position was in community organizing. Glascoe quickly became a leader at Restoration; serving as director of community programs, manager of Restoration Plaza, and as assistant to Restoration president Franklin Thomas. In 1981, Glascoe joined the Consolidated Edison team, where he served as manager of public affairs and director of economic development. During his retirement, Glascoe remained active on the boards of Restoration, the East Harlem Council for Economic Improvement, and the Transfiguration Education Association.
  In this interview, Benjamin A. Glascoe remembers the racially integrated Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn of his youth; and details his education. Glascoe provides his impressions of Bedford-Stuyvesant in the 1960s. He recalls his different roles at Restoration. As the director of community programs, Glascoe revamped a problematic public sanitation program, installed youth programming, and created a successful jobs training program called the Home Improvement Program. Glascoe recounts an era of financial difficulty for Restoration, when the organization was penalized and significantly de-funded by the federal government because they had invested federal monies with the plan to use the proceeds as their operating budget. At one moment, Glascoe becomes emotional when remembering his son, the firefighter Keith Glascoe, who perished in the aftermath of the September 11th attacks on the World Trade Center. Finally, Glascoe shares his optimism for Restoration's future. Interview conducted by Brian Purnell.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Cultural facilities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Merchants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Glascoe, Benjamin; Grannum, Colvin W.; Thomas, Franklin A.
- Grannum, Colvin, 2008 January 8; 2008.030.16
  Born in 1953, Colvin W. Grannum was raised in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, where he studied at P.S. 130 Elementary and Erasmus Hall High School, and attended the Beulah Church of the Nazarene. He majored in religion at the University of Pennsylvania, received a law degree from Georgetown University, and subsequently practiced law for over seventeen years. After serving as the president of Bridge Street Community Development Corporation, Grannum was brought on as the president of Restoration. At the time of the 2008 interview, Grannum had held that position for over five years.
  In this interview, Colvin Grannum, president of Restoration, speaks of his work at the Bridge Street Development Corporation (a community development corporation) and Restoration, and differentiates between faith-based and non-church-affiliated CDCs. He reminisces about growing up in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, addresses the changes he's witnessed within the community, and discusses Restoration's role and opportunities in future development. He provides his thoughts on the United States' national politics and the 2008 presidential election. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  African American churches |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Religion |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Spirituality; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Bridge Street Development Corporation; Grannum, Colvin W.; Inniss, Charles E.
- Green, Pamela, 2008 February 5; 2008.030.17
  Pamela Green was born in Gulfport, Mississippi in 1948. Green has a bachelor's degree in mathematics and began her career in 1968. She has worked for International Business Machines (IBM) and First National Bank of Chicago. She was a commissioner with city government in New York until becoming an executive with the Children's Television Workshop, the production company of Sesame Street. After being laid off in 2001, she became Executive Director of what was then the Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. Green oversaw the restoration of historic homes on the site and a name change to the Weeksville Heritage Center in 2005. Three years later, plans for a new Education and Cultural Arts Building were implemented and building began. She retired from the center in summer of 2013. Green was a resident of Bedford-Stuyvesant in Brooklyn for decades, and also has a master's degree in finance from the University of Chicago.
  In this interview, Pamela Green, executive director of the Weeksville Heritage Center, provides a history of Weeksville, a post-enslavement community of free, land-owning African Americans founded circa 1838 in Brooklyn, New York. She tells of the discovery of Weeksville, the campaign for its conservation and preservation, and the establishment of the Heritage Center. She outlines Weeksville Heritage Center's plans for the development and expansion of public programming to provide a contemporary learning experience that emphasizes early post-enslavement African American culture and achievements. She names connections between the WHC and Restoration, outlays her idea of the proper role of community development corporations, and discusses the matriarchy of female Black community leaders in Brooklyn's recent history. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan with Bahati Williams.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Architecture |x Conservation and restoration; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 19th century; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Cultural facilities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Historic buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nonprofit organizations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Weeksville (New York, N.Y.); Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Green, Pamela; Maynard, Joan; Richardson, Elsie; Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History
- Gunn, Theodore, 2008 January 31; 2008.030.18
  The artist Theodore "Teddy" Gunn, born 1931, was raised primarily in the Upstate New York town of Saugerties before moving with his family to the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan. During a lengthy career, Gunn worked with many of New York City's most respected arts and cultural institutions. In his thirty-two-year career with Restoration, he served as the director of the Center for Arts and Culture from 1970 to 1994. He served as a founding trustee, acting director, and exhibition coordinator at Harlem's Studio Museum; and served as a member of the Metropolitan Museum of Art's Committee for Community Programs. He served on the board of directors of many of New York City's influential institutions, including the Brooklyn Arts and Cultural Association, the Brooklyn Masonic Temple, the Washington Heights Arts Show, and The Rotunda Gallery. He died in 2020.
  In this interview, Theodore "Teddy" Gunn discusses his introduction to Restoration at its inception, in the 1960s. He describes the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood and community of Brooklyn around that era, and how it's progressed over the last thirty years. Gunn calls its evolution, gentrification, and eventual inclusion of many races and peoples "totally American." He speaks of his thirty-two-year career with Restoration, and reflects on Restoration's role in shepherding community improvements via social, cultural, educational, and outreach programming. Gunn also describes his proudest achievements and legacy at Restoration. Interview conducted by Judith Anglin.
  Art |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Cultural facilities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nonprofit organizations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Philanthropists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Gunn, Theodore; Inniss, Charles E.; Kennedy, Robert F.; Thomas, Franklin A.
- Javits, Carla, 2008 February 4; 2008.030.19
  Carla Javits was one of United States Senator from New York Jacob Javits's three children. She held a bachelor's degree and a master's in public policy from the University of California, Berkeley. Carla Javits' father, along with Senator Robert F. Kennedy, created the Economic Opportunity Act that led to Restoration's initial funding, and subsequently laid the groundwork for its establishment. At that time, Carla Javits was around ten years old. Javits was the former President and Chief Executive Officer (CEO) of the Corporation for Supportive Housing and later became the President and CEO of the Roberts Enterprise Development Fund, which continued her twenty-five year career in advocacy for the homeless and disadvantaged.
  In this interview, Carla Javits discusses her father, Senator Jacob Javits, and his involvement in laying the groundwork for, and establishing, Restoration. She explains Restoration's role as an inspiration for other community development corporations (CDCs), as well as the necessity of federal financial support for the success of CDCs. At the interview's end, Javits touches on her current professional and philanthropic activities in non-profit organizations concerned with human development. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Communities; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Legislators |z United States; United States |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Corporation for Supportive Housing; Javits, Carla; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel); Kennedy, Robert F.
- Katz, Noah, 2008 May 21; 2008.030.20
  Noah Katz (born 1966), along with his brother Daniel and father Sidney, owned and operated the Super FoodTown located in Restoration Plaza. While the Katz family owned grocery stores throughout New York City, they considered the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn location to be their flagship. At the time of the 2008 interview, the store had been open almost five years. The Katz family were active participant members of the Fulton-Nostrand Merchant's Association, and Noah Katz served as co-chairman of the Bedford-Stuyvesant Gateway Business Improvement District (BID) campaign committee.
  In this interview, Noah Katz relates his family's early interest in opening a Super FoodTown grocery store inside the Bedford Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn's Restoration Plaza. He recounts the effort to renovate the location's footprint from its previous incarnation into a larger, upscale version -- a feat which Katz served as general contractor and completed in ninety days. Katz reflects on the importance of grocery stores in close-knit communities and counts the benefits of strong supermarkets: They are a local source of employment, a place to encounter neighbors, and of course, a convenient location in which to purchase groceries. Katz enumerates his family's charitable contributions to the Bedford-Stuyvesant community, including donations to Restoration. Finally Katz tells of his work with the Fulton-Nostrand Merchant's Association, in which he and his family are active participant members, and his work with the Bedford-Stuyvesant Gateway Business Improvement District (BID). Katz served as the co-chairman of that BID's campaign committee. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Markets |z New York (State) |z New York; Philanthropists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association; Katz, Noah
- Keller, Thomas, 2008 February 9; 2008.030.21
  The New York-area real estate developer Thomas B. Keller, born in 1931 in Toledo, Ohio, left home at age fourteen to join the United States Army. Upon release from the Army in 1948, Keller moved to Brooklyn, New York, where he began working for the city government on a home improvement project. Hired by Restoration in 1967, the year of its incorporation, Keller quickly advanced to hold the vice presidency of Restoration's for-profit subsidiary corporation, and assumed responsibility for the construction of Restoration's 300,000-square-foot corporate headquarters -- which comprised the Restoration offices along with a Pathmark Supermarket, the Billie Holiday Theatre, and 800 units of affordable housing. In his fifty-year career, Keller gained prominence as a respected general contractor, construction manager, and real estate development consultant notable for breaking racial barriers in the New York City construction industry. After leaving Restoration, Keller founded the Brisa Builders Corporation. He died in 2015.